Henry Sapoznik collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
Henry Sapoznik collection circa 1920-1960
AFC 2010/003
Sapoznik, Henry
10,438 items; 25 containers (not including audiovisual materials); 148 linear inches (not including audiovisual materials).
1401 sound discs: analog; 16 in. and various sizes.
546 sound tape reels: analog; 10 in.
4 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in.
8400 items.
84 photographs: black and white, color; various sizes.
3 items.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection of Yiddish radio broadcasts on transcription discs and audio tape; plus sheet music, manuscripts and photographs documenting Yiddish culture, theater, and music, primarily in the New York City area, but also including documentation from other parts of the United States, from the 1920s to circa 1960, collected by Henry Sapoznik. Manuscripts include correspondence, manuscript music, photocopies, and other material.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Sapoznik, Henry
Subjects
Authors, Yiddish.; Ethnic radio broadcasting--New York (State)--New York.; Folk songs, Yiddish.; Jews--New York (State)--New York--Social life and customs.; Radio broadcasting, Yiddish--New York (State)--New York.; Radio broadcasting, Yiddish--United States.; Songs, Yiddish.; Theater, Yiddish.
Form/Genre
Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Photographs.; Radio programs.; Sound recordings.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: 1: Radio broadcasting; 2: Radio writers, performers, and programs; 3: Organizations and committees; 4: Print publications; 5: Interview transcripts, logs, and related documentation; 6: Manuscripts accompanying sound recordings; 7: "The Stations that Spoke Your Language": Yiddish-American Radio 1925-1955; 8: Sound recordings; 9: Photographic materials; 10: Artifacts.
Acquisition
Henry Sapoznik; 2010, 2012.
Accruals
The 2012 accrual consisted of three items: the cut-out and mounted photo of Al Entin, the hand chimes and mallet, and a ticket stub.
Related Material
Hear, O Israel, Yiddish-American Broadcasting 1925-1965, Lecture by Henry Sapoznik (AFC 2009/013), Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Access may be restricted. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Additional Formats
Selected analog disc recordings have preservation tape masters in the collection.
Biographical Note
Henry Sapoznik was born in Brooklyn, New York City, in 1953. He is an author, record and radio producer, scholar, and performer of klezmer music. He directed the Mayrent Institute for Yiddish Culture at the University of Wisconsin, Madison, until his retirement in 2017.
Scope and Content
Collection of Yiddish radio broadcasts on transcription discs and audio tape; plus sheet music, manuscripts and photographs documenting Yiddish culture, theater, and music, primarily in the New York City area, but also including documentation from other parts of the United States, from the 1920s to circa 1960, collected by Henry Sapoznik. Manuscripts include correspondence, manuscript music, photocopies, and other material.
Container List
- Series 1: Radio broadcasting
  Documentation includes original materials and photocopies, as well as faxes and ditto copies. If no date is given then the information was not available. Materials in Yiddish and English. Includes correspondence, the background and history of stations, publicity for stations and featured performers, continuity guidelines, radio licenses and applications for renewal,
  - Subseries A: History, programs, legal documents, and related materials
    Materials in Yiddish and English. Includes correspondence, the background and history of stations, publicity for stations and featured performers, continuity guidelines, radio licenses and applications for renewal.
    - NBC: religious programming policy, 1935 (Box-folder 1/1)
      Original documents and photocopies.
    - WABC, 1929 (Box-folder 1/2)
      Photocopies.
    - WADS and WAVZ, 1950s (Box-folder 1/3)
      Original documents.
    - WARD, circa 1940s-2000s (Box-folder 1/4)
    - WBBC, 1920s-1930s; 2000s (Box-folder 1/5)
      Original documents and copies.
    - WBNX, 1920s-1940s (Box-folder 1/6)
      Photocopies, plus one original brochure (circa 1930s).
    - WCFL, 1920s-1930s (Box-folder 1/7)
    - WEDC, 1930s-1940s (Box-folder 1/8)
    - WEVD, 1920s (Box-folder 1/9)
    - WEVD, 1940s (Box-folder 1/10)
    - WEVD, 1950s (Box-folder 2/1)
    - WEVD, 1960s (Box-folder 2/2)
    - WEVD, 1970s-1990s (Box-folder 2/3)
    - WEVD, 2000s (Box-folder 2/4)
      One original document and a newspaper clipping.
    - WEVD: Debs Memorial Radio Fund, 1920, 1932 (Box-folder 2/5)
      Photocopied documents on the background of WEVD as a radio station operating in memory of Eugene Debs. Includes a 1992 letter to Henry Sapoznik from Paul F. Gullifor, Bradley University.
    - WEVD: Debs Memorial Radio Fund stock books (1 of 3) (Box-folder 2/6)
      Includes originals and copies of newspaper clippings, correspondence and radio license renewal documents. A fax to Henry Sapoznik (1992) is also included.
    - WEVD: Debs Memorial Radio Fund stock books (2 of 3) (Box-folder 2/7)
      Includes a program from the dedication of the new WEVD building (1938). See description for box-folder 2/6.
    - WEVD: Debs Memorial Radio Fund stock books (3 of 3) (Box-folder 2/8)
      Includes a verified reception stamp and handwritten notes on yellow legal paper. See description for box-folder 2/6.
    - WEVD: Debs Memorial Radio Fund, Inc.: stock certificates 1-25, 1928-1932 (Box-folder 2/9)
      Bound oblong volume with original stock certificates (some detached), bearing stock transfer tax stamps.
    - WEVD: Debs Memorial Radio Fund, Inc.: stock certificates 25-50, 1933-1939 (Box-folder 2/10)
      Bound oblong volume with original stock certificates (some detached).
    - WEVD: FRC and FCC documents (1 of 8), 1926-1957, 1991 (Box-folder 3/1)
      Includes originals and photocopies of FRC and FCC documents, radio licenses and applications for license renewals, correspondence, newspaper articles, financial information regarding the Debs Memorial Fund, Inc., program information, and related documentation.
    - WEVD: FRC and FCC documents (2 of 8), 1926-1957, 1991 (Box-folder 3/2)
      The contents date primarily from the 1920s. See description for box-folder 3/1.
    - WEVD: FRC and FCC documents (3 of 8), 1926-1957, 1991 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - WEVD: FRC and FCC documents (4 of 8), 1926-1957, 1991 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - WEVD: FRC and FCC documents (5 of 8), 1926-1957, 1991 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - WEVD: FRC and FCC documents (6 of 8), 1926-1957, 1991 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - WEVD: FRC and FCC documents (7 of 8), 1926-1957, 1991 (Box-folder 3/7)
      Documents are from 1953-1991.
    - WEVD: FRC and FCC documents (8 of 8), 1926-1957, 1991 (Box-folder 3/8)
      Two issues of the news flyer, "What's Nu!" (one from 1954, the other undated).
    - Sections of the FBI report on radio station WEVD (2 folders), 1940s-1970s; 1994 (Box-folder 3/9-10)
      Includes original letter from the FBI to Andy Lanset, who had requested the report. The report is photocopied, with information redacted in the source copy.
    - Henry Sapoznik's WEVD file, 1990 (Box-folder 3/11)
      Original documents. Includes correspondence to Sapoznik while he worked at WEVD, and a program script in transcribed Yiddish.
    - WEVD, 1950s, undated (Box-folder 3/12)
      Copy of a letter from the Yiddish Radio Guild of America, an original page and two photocopies from WEVD English and foreign language program schedules, and an original document called "Who's Who among advertisers on WEVD."
    - WHN (1 of 2), 1920s, undated (Box-folder 4/1)
      Originals and photocopies.
    - WHN (2 of 2), 1927-1941 (Box-folder 4/2)
      Photocopies of license application documents, program analysis sheet, and related materials.
    - WHOM, 1938-1950 (Box-folder 4/3)
      45th anniversary program schedule for the station, legal papers, correspondence, and newspaper articles. Original documents and photocopies.
    - WJLB, undated (Box-folder 4/4)
      Two-page photocopy of Weinberg's Yiddish radio hour (a memoir), by Harry Weinberg.
    - WLIB, 1942, undated (Box-folder 4/5)
      Original documents. Master program schedule for September 1942, and an radio station profile prepared for Sapoznik.
    - WLTH (originals and photocopies), 1935-1947 (Box-folder 4/6)
      Original documents and photocopies. Correspondence to Victor Packer, program advertisements, a songster in Yiddish and English, with music; program schedules, a station profile created for Sapoznik, and related documents.
    - Publication on the history of WNYC radio and TV (original), circa 1986 (Box-folder 4/7)
      Overview of WNYC's history.
    - "Lincoln and the Jews," by Emanuel Hertz, 1928 (Box-folder 4/8)
      Original copy of the text delivered on WRNY radio.
    - Brooklyn radio stations, 1928-1934, 1999, undated (Box-folder 4/9)
      Radio station profiles prepared for Sapoznik, newspaper articles, and related documents. Original documents and photocopies.
    - Raymond, Art. Put your money where your mouth is. 1978 (Box-folder 4/10)
      Original copy of a small book on finding a job in the radio industry.
    - "Recollections of Jewish Radio and Television," October 21, 1985 (Box-folder 4/11)
      Talk delivered by Sholom Rubinstein.
    - "Jewish Radio Stations," undated (Box-folder 4/12)
      Unpublished research report by Beatrice Goldsmith on Jewish radio stations. Faxed document, printed on regular bond paper.
  - Subseries B: Scripts and related materials
    Materials are in Yiddish.
    - Shulamis (Box-folder 4/13)
      Original copy of a script for the radio play, in Yiddish.
    - Tsvei Kuni Lemels (Box-folder 4/14)
- Series 2: Radio writers, performers, and programs
  Includes scripts, correspondence, and related documentation.
  - Subseries A: Nahum Stutchkoff
    - Bei Tate Mames Tish (Round the Family Table) (1 of 3), circa 1939 (Box-folder 5/1)
      Original, typed copy of a script for the program, in Yiddish; pencilled notations throughout, and housed in a black paper binder. The name of Max Friedlander is handwritten in pencil on the last page, with further notes. The folder also includes the typing paper package in which AFC received the document.
    - Bei Tate Mames Tish (Round the Family Table) (2 of 3), circa 1939 (Box-folder 5/2)
      Original, typed copy of the radio play, in Yiddish; pencilled writing and notations throughout, and housed in a tan paper binder.
    - Bei Tate Mames Tish (Round the Family Table) (3 of 3), circa 1939 (Box-folder 5/3)
      Original, typed, unbound copy of the radio play, in Yiddish. This may be a draft or revision of the play. The folder also includes the typing paper package in which AFC received the document.
    - In a Yidisher Groseri (In a Jewish Grocery) (1 of 2), circa late 1930s (Box-folder 5/4)
      Photocopy of the radio play, with handwritten notations and orange highlighting.
    - In a Yidisher Groseri (In a Jewish Grocery) (2 of 2), circa late 1930s (Box-folder 5/5)
      See description for box-folder 5/2.
    - Radio appeals for a Jewish sanitorium, undated (Box-folder 5/6)
      Original, typed text in Yiddish with handwritten notations. The folder also includes the typing paper package in which AFC received the document. This was the Brooklyn Jewish Sanitarium, now called Kingsbrook Jewish Medical Center.
    - Publicity and articles, circa 1930s-1960s (Box-folder 5/7)
      Original documents and photocopies. Includes publicity and articles about Stutchkoff.
    - Note and envelope to Henry Sapoznik, January 2003 (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Subseries B: Wolf Younin
    These manuscripts were received as a group from the donor. Wolf Younin was, at one point, the secretary for the Yiddish Radio Guild of America.
    - Yiddish Radio Guild of America - correspondence (2 folders), 1942-1943, undated (Box-folder 6/1-2)
      Original documents; in Yiddish and English. Most are typed, with some documents and notes handwritten in pencil.
    - Yiddish Radio Guild of America - scripts, undated (Box-folder 6/3)
      Original documents; in Yiddish.
    - Wolf Younin - scripts and correspondence, 1941-1943, undated (Box-folder 6/4)
      Original documents, typed and handwritten; in Yiddish and English.
    - Wolf Younin: advertising copy (2 folders), 1943, undated (Box-folder 6/5-6)
    - Yiddish Radio Guild of America: news scripts and advertisements, 1943-1944, undated (Box-folder 6/7)
      See description for box-folder 6/4.
    - Texts, bills, and related documentation, 1943-1949, undated (Box-folder 6/8)
      See description for box-folder 6/4. Includes bills signed by Younin for fees charged to translate particular texts from English to Yiddish.
    - Misha Rapel, 1943, undated (Box-folder 6/9)
      Embossed image (on paper) of Misha Rapel; 2 1/3 in. x 2 1/2 in. Rappel, also known as Maurice Rappel and as Morris Rappaport, was a Yiddish-language radio and stage personality.
  - Subseries C: Correspondence to radio stations
    Postcards and brief notes with envelopes, plus other materials related to the radio stations. Some notes do not have an accompanying envelope, and some envelopes are empty. A significant number of items are specifically addressed to Wolf Younin, who worked both at WARD and WBYN radio stations.
    - Correspondence to WARD (4 folders), 1940 (Box-folder 7/1-4)
      Correspondence from listeners in response to trivia questions or requests for stories, or requesting publications.
    - Correspondence to WARD (2 folders), 1941 (Box-folder 7/5-6)
      See description for box-folder 7/1.
    - Manuscripts accompanying correspondence to WARD, circa 1940s, 1975 (Box-folder 7/7)
      Includes newspaper clippings, handwritten notes, and one two-page typed document. Almost all texts in Yiddish.
    - Correspondence to WBYN (3 folders), 1941 (Box-folder 7/8-10)
      Correspondence, as brief notes or as postcards, from WBYN listeners to WBYN or Wolf Younin, to request tickets to a radio show, or to send stamps to him to cover postage for a Purim Megillah in Yiddish to be sent to them, as Younin had announced on the air. Some messages are in Yiddish, but most are in English. Some envelopes are empty. Note: some people write Younin's name as "Union," or similar variations. WBYN existed as such from 1941-1946.
    - Correspondence to WBYN (2 folders), 1942 (Box-folder 8/1-2)
      See description for box-folder 7/8. Also included: an invitation from Mr. and Mrs. Sholom Secunda to the Bar Mitzvah of their son, Sheldon. Shalom Fecundate was a noted Yiddish composer, and his son later became a songwriter.
    - Correspondence to WBYN (1-7 of 38), 1943 (Box-folder 8/3-9)
      See description for box-folder 7/8.
    - Correspondence to WBYN (8-16 of 38), 1943 (Box-folder 9/1-9)
    - Correspondence to WBYN (17-26 of 38), 1943 (Box-folder 10/1-10)
    - Correspondence to WBYN (27-36 of 38), 1943 (Box-folder 11/1-10)
    - Correspondence to WBYN (37-38 of 38), 1943 (Box-folder 12/1-2)
    - Correspondence to WBYN, undated (Box-folder 12/3)
    - Correspondence to WEVD, 1943 (Box-folder 12/4)
  - Subseries D: Radio personalities and performers
    - Jan Bart, circa 1944-1998 (Box-folder 12/5)
      Includes typed radio dialog and correspondence. Originals and photocopies.
    - Hyman Brown, circa 2003 (Box-folder 12/6)
      Typed biography by Patricia J. Priest and a newspaper clipping.
    - Henry Burbig, 1929 (Box-folder 12/7)
      One-page texts in Yinglish of humorous radio copy, ultimately used to advertise products made by CeCo Manufacturing Co. Photocopies.
    - Chaver-Paver (1 of 2), undated (Box-folder 12/8)
      Lobzig the Crisis Dog, by Chaver-Paver (the professional name of Gershon Einbinder). Ditto copies of the radio episodes. In Yiddish.
    - Chaver-Paver (2 of 2), 1939 (Box-folder 12/9)
      See note for box-folder 12/8. Photocopies of credits and narration, in English.
    - Benjamin A. Gebiner, May 22, 1993 (Box-folder 12/10)
      Original program from the Mensch of the Year Award buffet luncheon, in honor of Gebiner.
    - Jacob Gordin, circa 1940s-1950s (Box-folder 12/11)
      Got, Mensch, und Tayvl (God, Man and Devil), adapted for the radio. Original and copies, in Yiddish and English.
    - Louis J. Gross, circa 1950s (Box-folder 12/12)
      Publicity for radio shows and events, and four business cards, including one for Gross. Originals, plus a few photocopies. In Yiddish and English.
    - Aaron Hantin (1 of 2), circa 1930-1940 (Box-folder 12/13)
      Includes correspondence, an original copy of Hagadah shel Pesah mit myuzik noten (Passover haggadah with music) in Hebrew and English (1912), texts of radio announcements, typed documents with handwritten notations, and handwritten music (with typed lyrics) for the song "Bar Mitzvo," by Evo (?) Silver and arranged by M. Kortchmaroff, drafts of WVFW (radio station) documents, and business cards. Documents are in Yiddish and English. A photograph was relocated to Series 3.
    - Aaron Hantin (2 of 2), circa 1930-1940 (Box-folder 12/14)
      See description for box-folder 12/13.
    - Joseph Jacobs, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 13/1)
      Includes original advertisements, advertising rates, and a letter of correspondence from Jacobs to Alexander Kahm (of The Jewish Daily Forward. Documents are in English.
    - Samuel Kaplan, circa 1940s; 1992-1994 (Box-folder 13/2)
      A newspaper obituary for Kaplan, a typed program list for WEVD (on the radio station's letterhead), a handwritten letter from Kaplan to Andy Lanset (accompanied by photocopied newspaper articles). A photograph was relocated to Series 3.
    - C. Israel Lutsky, circa 1922-1999 (Box-folder 13/3)
      Includes correspondence, published materials, pages from a calendar, and a synopsis of Lutsky's radio segments. Originals and photocopies; in English.
    - Samuel P. Mogelewsky, 1935 (Box-folder 13/4)
      Two pages (both photocopies) of radio station advertisements. In Yiddish.
    - Victor Packer, 1958; undated (Box-folder 13/5)
      An advertisement for a play, which includes Packer's name and image (the advertisement, dated 1958, is in Yiddish and English), and a 7-page typed document in Yiddish (undated).
    - Samuel Regensberg, 2001; undated (Box-folder 13/6)
      One photocopied item of publicity (in Yiddish and English), and a handwritten letter from Regenberg's daughter Juliet Halpern (original; in English). A photo was relocated to Series 3.
    - Vera Rosanko, 1946; undated (Box-folder 13/7)
      Publicity (original; in Yiddish and English), and several pages of handwritten musical notation, including the following compositions: "L'chaim Rosy-Vilner," "Kinder Yorn," "Mother's Day," "Vera Vilner," "Mazel Tov Mames," "Leby," and "My Yiddishe Mame." Some notations pencilled in Yiddish.
    - Zvee Scooler, 1937-1985; undated (Box-folder 13/8)
      Photocopied materials, including Scooler's obituary and the transcript of an interview with Scooler (1977). Also includes a program for a 1982 event honoring Zvee Scooler. In Yiddish and English.
    - Chaim Towber, circa 1967 (Box-folder 13/9)
      An original pamphlet, in Yiddish, celebrating the life and achievements of Chaim Towber.
    - Baruch Charney Vladeck, 1923-1993 (Box-folder 13/10)
      Photocopy of a biography of Vladeck, published in American Jewish Yearbook, 1939, typed notes from an unidentified person who looked at the Vladeck papers at Tamiment Library, New York University (and photocopied correspondence from that collection), a photocopied speech by Vladeck from his papers at Tamiment, and a typed, original letter from Norman Thomas to Vladeck. Documents in English.
    - Zalmen and Celia Zylbercweig, 1953-1997 (Box-folder 13/11)
      Includes printed advertising Zalmen and Celia's radio show, photocopied obituaries for Celia, a program for the fiftieth anniversary of their radio show, and correspondence. In Yiddish and English.
- Series 3: Organizations and committees
  - American Jewish Congress – related documents (photocopies) from the papers of Rabbi J.K. Cohen, ca. 1935-, circa 1935-1938; undated (Box-folder 13/12)
    Includes photocopied documents from the papers of Rabbi J.K. Cohen, and a handwritten (original) note from Daniel Soyer (researcher). The original copies of Rabbi Cohen's documents are held at Stephen Wise Free Synagogue, in folder 164.
  - American Red Cross Bureau of Foreign Language Information Service., April 16, 1920 (Box-folder 13/13)
    Photocopy of a typed letter from an individual (Robert A. Bo--?) to William F. Keohan, at the Department of Justice, regarding the potential Communist sympathies of the FLIS.
  - Citizens Committee on Displaced Persons (CCDP), 1947-1949 (Box-folder 13/14)
    Minutes of meetings (photocopies).
  - Common Council for American Unity (CCAU) (5 folders), circa 1939-1943 (Box-folder 13/15-16, 14/1-3)
    Includes photocopied correspondence, newspaper and media coverage, information on foreign-language radio broadcasts in the United States, scripts for radio programs, and documentation to support the mission and work of the CCAU through radio broadcasts.
  - How about putting your union on the air, undated (Box-folder 14/4)
    Original brochure, published by the Jewish Labor Committee.
  - Message of Israel, 1947-1953 (Box-folder 14/5)
    Original, typed copies of seven radio scripts for the program Message of Israel and presented by the American Jewish Layman's Committee. Also includes pieces of original envelopes.
  - United Service for New Americans (USNA) (1 of 2), circa 1948-1954 (Box-folder 14/6)
    Includes correspondence, an interview transcript, memos, and newspaper clippings related to the radio broadcast content. Originals and photocopies.
  - United Service for New Americans (USNA) (2 of 2), circa 1948-1954 (Box-folder 14/7)
    See description for box-folder 14/6.
  - Works Progress Administration (WPA) (1 of 2), 1935-1993 (Box-folder 14/8)
    Includes correspondence, programming information, scripts of radio plays, documents pertaining to the Jewish Division of the Federal Theatre of the Air, and a copy of a report on "Cultural Diversity in the Federal Theatre Project." Originals and photocopies.
  - Works Progress Administration (WPA) (2 of 2) (Box-folder 14/9)
    See description for box-folder 14/8.
- Series 4: Print publications
  Includes publicity, graphics, and sheet music from various publications, grouped by name, then by general categories.
  - Amerikaner, circa 1930 (Box-folder 15/1)
    Photocopies of several pages. Primarily in Yiddish, with some English.
  - The Broadcaster, March 1934 (Box-folder 15/2)
    The periodical was the official organ of the Radio Synagogue of America. Photocopy of complete issue.
  - The Broadcaster, March 1935 (Box-folder 15/3)
    See note for box-folder 13/13,
  - Der Tog (newspaper): articles and advertisements, circa 1920s; 1993 (Box-folder 15/4)
    Includes typed research reports on the Der Tog radio show from Daniel Soyer, and numerous photocopies from the pages of the newspaper Der Tog. The newspaper made more than one attempt to broadcast a radio show., Originals and photocopies.
  - Forward: articles and advertisements, circa 1929-1933 (Box-folder 15/5)
    Photocopies, almost entirely in Yiddish.